wasabi wallet
unfairly private
the lightning network is a second layer
built on top of bitcoin that allows for
cheaper and faster transactions it
allows the network as a whole to scale
to millions of transactions per
second now there are many different ways
to interact with the lightning network
including
custodial and non-custodial apps that
you can simply
install on your mobile device or you can
go the full mile
and run a full lightning node which is
exactly
what we're going to be covering today i
am ben with the btc sessions
and this is your daily session
[Music]
before we dive in of course a quick
shout out to sponsors of the show
len io this is where you can use your
bitcoin for a variety of different
services
of course they have their bitcoin backed
loans which is primarily what i have
used them for and
this really helps if you're in a pinch
and you need to get your hands on
dollars but you don't want to sell your
bitcoin because of course
that is a taxable event and two you
might be worried
about having a buy back in at a higher
price so here you're able to deposit
bitcoin get dollars to your bank account
within 24 hours
and when you pay those dollars back you
get back the exact same amount of
bitcoin
of course they also have their bitcoin
and usdc savings accounts with interest
rates of up to 12 and a half percent
annually paid monthly and they've got
their b2x offering which uses the
same loan mechanism to instantly buy you
more bitcoin if you're feeling
mega bullish there's a link to check
them out in the show notes down below
and if you click that link and off to
get either the loan products they'll
give you 25 bucks for free into your
savings
up next we have bit refill now i do live
on bitcoin and one of the
things that really helps me do this is
bit refill in that they have
just every damn gift card you can
imagine in just about every country
you could imagine so you can head over
here and you can easily
get anything you need paid for with
bitcoin either
on the main chain or conveniently
conveniently as we're covering it today
on the lightning network of course you
also earn sats back
as you shop which is wonderful and
they've got a pretty killer referral
program as well
links for that will be down below and
finally
if you're backing up any bitcoin wallet
including
the node that you are using today
for your lightning wallet um
it's a good idea to do so securely and
sometimes a piece of paper
is not always the best option so
something on solid steel like the bill
fotl can
save you from things like fire damage
water damage or
just somebody accidentally throwing out
that slip of paper
so please give yourself that peace of
mind i've heard some horror stories as
of late and
this solid piece of steel with little
tiles where you slide in to
back up your seed phrase is exactly how
i back up
all major important seed phrases for
wallets that i have so be sure to check
them out and with that let's dive
into the tutorial
now if you are just starting with
bitcoin
running a lightning node is probably not
going to be your first step
there are some prerequisites that you
should likely have before diving in
here and so i'm going to bring up some
of those so
if you are at that point then wonderful
we can go ahead but if you're not
probably good to go back and do some
basic learning first so let's take a
look at some things that might be
beneficial to you
first um first up of course bitcoin
basics
things like where to get bitcoin how to
use a regular bitcoin wallet
even maybe a little bit of security
about how to use a hardware device
stuff like that is very beneficial um
also a general knowledge of bitcoin fees
how to set
transaction fees things like that all of
those will really help you along the way
using a lightning node and i do have a
playlist called getting started
you can find it and you can kind of pick
through some of those
videos to help you along your way now
up next you also do need
to have a bitcoin node a full bitcoin
node not just a lightning node
a full bitcoin node running a copy of
the bitcoin blockchain
now today i'm going to be using umbral
uh but you can also use my node and
there are some other setups that you can
use as well but i have done tutorials
for both of those both umbral
and my node they're a little bit
different so if you're running my node
it's going to look a little bit
different for you
to utilize the programs we're using
today but in general if you don't have a
node go back
use this umbral video to get yourself
set up
really really simple to get it rolling
so get yourself a bitcoin note if you
don't have one already
and then finally a little bit of basic
knowledge about lightning
would be incredibly beneficial and what
i was what i'm talking about here is
maybe you should play around a little
bit
with a non-lightning node
intensive you know all the nitty gritty
first
just to familiarize yourself with how to
receive and send
transactions and that will also help you
here so that it
isn't as foreign when you get into the
nitty-gritty
of running everything i do have
tutorials on that i would recommend
checking out things like breeze or
phoenix
if you want to really easy just jump in
try a few transactions and then jump in
here
then something like the custodial
version of blue wallet
or wallet of satoshi will be just fine
for you
but with that said let's chat a little
bit about a lightning node and what it
entails
so let's discuss lightning channels
because
this is going to be the bulk of our
learning with this tutorial
what is a lightning channel well
effectively it is the act of a locking
up
bitcoin between two peers in a multi-sig
so that you can effectively allocate
which bitcoin belongs to who and do a
bunch of tiny transactions
off-chain before settling to the main
bitcoin blockchain
so let's do a hypothetical let's say you
were a bartender who under
who owned a bar i'm a patron and
i could settle every single time you
bring me a drink this would be like
doing a bitcoin
transaction every time a beer comes over
to the table
however that's not efficient the fees
would be not great and if everybody did
that the blockchain would be so bogged
down it would be
difficult to get a transaction through
we'd be waiting for final settlement so
and so forth
now with lightning the way this would
happen is
i would lock up a hundred dollars in a
tab with you
and every time you brought me over a
drink i would allocate
five dollars of my hundred dollar pool
over to you so this is effectively a
contract
of that locked up bitcoin so let's say
by the end of the night you brought me
over five beers i
gave you five dollars each time and so
now the contract between us with that
locked up bitcoin says you get 25 bucks
and i keep
75 of that we're able to then close that
channel and settle that to the main
bitcoin blockchain
only having done two actual on-chain
transactions one creating the multi-sig
and one closing it out and oftentimes
these channels
don't ever really need to be closed uh
or very seldom need to be closed
so that that effectively could be left
open
if i decided to come back another time
okay
so that's the basics behind it let's
take a look at a visualization that
shows something like that
so here's an example of a channel open
between
alice and bob alice has said hey i'm
going to be transacting with bob a fair
amount what i'm going to do is i'm going
to lock up this bitcoin here
and if i want to pay him i can bump it
over to his
side of the channel and if either of us
any either have a dispute or just want
to go our separate ways we can close the
channel
and settle so if alice wants to pay bob
say two bitcoin it would look like this
she just bumps those bitcoin over to his
side of the channel
again at any point either of them can
leave and keep their own
bitcoin as the updated version
of that contract now where it gets
interesting
is if bob is also connected to another
peer
let's say bob is also connected to carol
he has created his own
lightning channel with her at this point
alice now has the option to also pay
carol
through bob and so let's say alice
wanted to send
two bitcoin to carol she could do that
by sending two to bob
and then bob sends two to carol and that
would look like this
two moved over to bob and bob bounce
that down the line to carol and this is
enforced through contracts so
it's not like bob can just steal the
money in the middle
a little animation of how this would
look you can see alice
bumps money to bob bob bumps money to
carol just like that
now normally you wouldn't just have a
single channel open with
an individual you would have multiple
channels open to
multiple well-connected other
individuals or other notes
and let's take a look at this really
cool graphic here
and i'll just unclick but this is the
lightning network as it stands right now
and these are all participants who have
a lightning nodes
if i zoom in we can click on an
individual who has
a lightning network node and we can see
all of their connections
you can see quite a few of them here
they're pretty
they've got a fair number of channels
and let's just take a look
at where they're connected now of course
this individual
can do transactions with all of the
nodes that they're
currently connected with but they can
also do transactions with all of the
nodes
that any of their connections are
connected with so let's take a look
there's a channel here leading to this
larger node
and look at all the peers that this
individual has
and not only that but this individual is
connected over to
this large node over here and look at
that
look at the amount of possible pathways
of connecting with peers here so you can
see very quickly there's like this
six degrees of kevin bacon effect where
if you've got a few good connections you
effectively can reach
everyone very easily with a transaction
now there is some other stuff to
consider here um
you have to consider uh a little bit
about the size of your channels
because in this first instance with
alice she has a limited amount of
bitcoin that she can send
and when bob was connected to carol here
he has a limited amount of bitcoin if he
only had
one bitcoin locked up between him and
carol
and she wanted to send two like alice
wanted to send to
that transaction wouldn't work because
there'd be a bottleneck so
you got to consider the size of your
channels and how you're going to be
transacting as well
we will get into that but this hopefully
was a decent little primer
to get your head around how lightning
channels
and liquidity works let's get into
actually doing this thing
so first things first let's get kind of
an overview of what we're going to be
looking at here
if you have not set up an umbral node or
if you're using my node then
one you've got to get a node going so be
sure to head back and do that
but if you're using my node the
interface will look a little bit
different but
this concepts are still generally the
same within your node you're going to
have two separate wallets you're gonna
have a bitcoin wallet
and a lightning wallet all right these
are also accessible
via the side here now your bitcoin
wallet is going to need to have
funds in it in order to load up the
lightning wallet
so very easy to do that within your
bitcoin wallet you just hit deposit
you're greeted with your address via qr
code and
uh down below and again part of the
prerequisite is knowing how to use
bitcoin
regular transactions as is so be sure to
load that up and
send yourself some bitcoins so that you
have it sitting on your
node now the lightning wallet i did show
in my umbrella tutorial
okay i did show that previously however
this is not how we're going to be
interacting with lightning today
it is important to know that any apps
within umbral
that reference lightning will be all
just ways of interacting
with this particular lightning node it's
all the same it's just different ways of
looking at it
okay so what we're going to be using
today is something within the app store
so since doing my original umbral
node video they have added an app store
where you can download a whole bunch of
different stuff
you can see over here there's four
different options and eventually there
may be more
for lightning node management they have
ride the lightning lightning terminal
thunderhub
and ln bits today i'm going to be using
thunderhub primarily and we will pop
into lightning terminal once
just to do something but i will go in
depth with lightning terminal in another
video but for now i have my apps again i
can go to my
apps tab here and i can see thunderhub
and i can just click on it and open it
up
now i do already have it open so let's
just take a look at that
and i'll get back to the home page here
this is what you will see when you first
land
and of course i already have funds in
lightning and on my umbrella notes so
it'll look a little bit different and i
already have channels going
so yours will be a little bit more bare
initially but let's look at what's in
front of us on your home page you're
going to get a lot of basic stuff
um how much you've got sitting in
lightning how much you've got sitting in
bitcoin
you'll have your public key just
information based on your node if
somebody wants to connect
with you uh all of your quick actions
if you want to open a channel will be
down here if you want to take a look at
an invoice
all kinds of different stuff here
invoices and payments reports
any balances that you have incoming and
outgoing how much you're able to spend
and receive
lots of different information about
routes and
transactions going through and i'm kind
of glossing this over because we'll get
to some of
it later you can click on your peers see
anybody that you currently have channels
open with
and your relationships with them again
you can get more details
on channels that you're using and in
incoming and outgoing transactions and
fees and all of that
you can rebalance your channels we'll
get into that concept later
um lots of great details throughout here
again
previous transactions you can take a
look at
any transactions that have been
forwarded through your node and any
fees that you've collected from doing
that um any of your on-chain
transactions there's tools here in
regarding backups
swapping into and out of lightning
that's an option here
and stats about your node and
uh just in general if you've got a
really well connected node
stats in terms of if you're on a
kind of high ranking list in terms of
your node there's also settings down
below for whether you want to see in
sats
in bitcoin or in fiat dollars
and you can change between light mode
night mode
and dark mode so all of that is there
you also have settings up top in the
right hand
corner there's a toggle and you can set
things
over there as well okay so that's kind
of the basics of
what's in front of you for thunderhub
and
more or less we will be diving into the
details of that
in general but pretty much your your
side menu here is going to get you where
you need to go
and you've got a summary of all funds uh
up in the top
left now
we also want to familiarize ourselves
with
a website called one ml
and one ml is a website that
you can look up information in regards
to
other lightning nodes or your own
lightning nodes so
let's just look up mine as an example
so mine does have an alias it is named
btc sessions
but here it is right here and if i click
on my node
i can see my public key and this
is the information that anybody would
need just to connect and
create a channel with me um it gives you
some stats on your node and some of
these node rank
stats here um basically the idea is the
lower the number the better okay so
um it's ranking from one and then
downwards
so if you your node is often offline or
if it's
relatively new then your availability
will be relatively
low but as you've been on long online
longer
then this will reduce the number here
and so i can also see the capacity
in terms of other lightning nodes doing
pretty well
i'm a special case because i'm lucky
enough to have a number of people that
wanted to connect with me
but besides the point this kind of just
gives you an idea now
when you're looking to connect with
other people you're kind of looking for
lower values here you're looking for
an availability you know probably below
500 is is a good aim uh same with
depending on what you're looking to do
somewhat higher capacity
would be better but we'll get into the
details of that later
and uh the number of channels is also
another one to look
look at so you can see channel count
ranking it says that i've got 33
channels there and i'm decently up the
list for
the amount of connections so that's kind
of a roundabout way of using 1ml
you can also just go on there and browse
and look through it'll show you
some of the top capacity increases in
the top number of channels
you don't always necessarily want to
connect to
large channels because if you have other
people connecting through you
you'll find those channels tend to drain
because people are routing payments that
way
and you need to rebalance once in a
while again details we'll get into later
but you can just kind of go for a stroll
and one way that i like to do this is i
hit the directory
and you just pick a random type of node
like
productivity people can designate
their their type of node that they're
running um and then you can just kind of
look through and and see
okay so this person uh has about half a
bitcoin of capacity
going in and out and if i click on them
i can see
again availability 584 yeah
not fantastic but on its way down so
that's not bad
um and then i can also see people just
above or just below
this individual and then i can start
clicking through okay what about this
person
i've got a bit more capacity although
they're not as
available they had a little bit more
downtime okay let's go a couple more
up now this person has a lot of downtime
let's keep going
and you can just kind of start clicking
through
and seeing what might
be uh this person's doing all right so
availability 154
capacity 532
in and around that 500 range not bad
okay
not bad so this is an individual that
maybe you might want to open up a
channel with
you can also go to stats
and you can see their average channel
capacity this person has an
average channel capacity is of 0.045
bitcoin
around 2500 um
or i guess that would be 4.5 million
sats and the reason that's important to
look at
is because it depends on what size of
transactions
you are going to be sending if
somebody's average channel capacity is
only
50 bucks and you want to send 100 or 200
payments that's going to be a bottleneck
for you and if you
ever want to send a large transaction so
um
if i ever think i might send more than
2500 bucks through the lightning network
then maybe this isn't a good pier for me
to connect to because i
want an average channel capacity above
that
so all things to consider when you're
connecting to
another peer and you should be
somewhat picky with who you connect to
or who you tie up your own bitcoin with
because if it doesn't serve you if
you're not able to
route payments through them then you've
now locked up bitcoin
that kind of becomes useless to you and
you might need to close the channel
later
and that incurs on-chain fees so you got
to do this balancing act so just keep
that in mind
as you're opening channels but we're
going to dive into actually opening some
channels
right now
so we're gonna start diving in here and
what we're gonna do first
is we're going to set up a basic channel
so you saw me kind of peeking through
that website one ml before
looking at various nodes where i might
want to connect a channel
however you can also do this if you know
somebody
that has a lightning node and you would
like to create a channel
with them and so that's what i'm going
to be doing right now now i know
somebody that
uh has said that they wouldn't mind me
setting up a channel with them
or you know vice versa and so i'm gonna
do so now what they have sent me is
their public
key and on your node in thunderhub
it looks like this it's right here boom
that's the information that somebody
needs to know in order
to set up a channel with you in fact uh
what you
you'll end up doing is there's a little
little button that says onion
and you hit that and it copies the onion
address
that somebody needs in order to open a
channel with you
now i was able to search up this person
on one ml as well
to see their channel capacity all that
kind of stuff
and you'll notice that their public key
is above and down below is the full
onion address and this is what we need
to open a channel with them
so really simply what i'm going to do is
i copy this information
and maybe somebody sends it via message
to you whatever
as long as you have that information
you're good and then i just go to
thunderhub
and just part way down the page you're
going to see a button that says open
this is going to open up a set of
possible places where you could open
channels with where they suggest
but you want a manual open so you're
going to hit
the open button to give you all those
options
now first it asks you is this a new
person a new peer that you're connecting
with yes
it is so i'm going to hit yes now is
this
uh it asks for the new node information
and that's where we're going to paste in
the information we just copied
okay next it says what channel
size do you want how much do you want to
be able to spend between you and this
person
i'm going to set it for 1 million
satoshi's
now the reason i'm doing that is
anything below
a million satoshi's can be a little bit
more difficult to
maintain and what i mean is the on-chain
fees of opening and closing that channel
can cut into
kind of what you're trying to do you can
open smaller channels of course you can
do five hundred thousand two hundred and
fifty thousand sats
it just depends on what you're trying to
do and i like to have
slightly bigger channels so that i don't
run into bottlenecks
if i'm trying to send out so i'm gonna
do a million sats and
it says do you want to push tokens to a
partner
so this means if i want to also pay the
person in the process
while i'm setting up this channel that's
not the case we'll look at that later
now the type is this public or private
it's public it's fine
uh and then the fee the fee for uh
setting up the channel so the on-chain
transaction fee and so i will uh
open up the mempool here just to kind of
see where we're at now
fees right now are high okay it's a
little bit
busier today i will eat the fees
on opening these channels today because
i'm trying to get this tutorial done and
over with
but if you're setting up your note it's
in your best interest to wait till a
time
when the mempool kind of clears out a
little bit we did see that over the
weekend weekends tend to be a good time
particularly on
sundays it tends to clear out a little
bit so keep that in mind as you're
setting up your node
you can save some on fees if you're
waiting out here
for me you know i'm i want to get into
this
next couple of blocks here so i'm
probably going to drop
70 or 80 sats per bite i know that's uh
a lot i am overpaying a little bit but
that's okay
so you know i'll take that hit
okay and then that's it i have it's a
new pier
i have the information to connect i have
the channel size
um and then i have my sats per byte to
what i'm paying for my feed
open the channel i'm going to go ahead
and hit the open channel button
takes a second to process we should get
a notification in the top right corner
there we go
channel opened and now
if we go to channels
up at the top here what you'll see this
is a list of
all of your open channels any pending
channels and any closed channels so you
can see i already do have channels open
for you right now this will be blank but
you can click on pending
and you will and if it doesn't show you
just hit refresh
and then it will show and go back to
pending there we go
okay so i can see my pending channel
with cryptoconomy yes indeed the
bitcoin audible mr guy swann so that is
pending if i click on it
i get a drop down of all of the
information about it
um about his node capacity everything so
on and so forth
and i can even copy the transaction id
and go over to mempool and just paste it
in
and now i can watch that transaction
what will happen is
once it's confirmed and i believe it
needs
two confirmations if i'm not mistaken
once it is confirmed um with a couple
confirmations
then that channel will be open and i
will be able to use it as liquidity to
send
transactions out now keep in mind here
guy swann has not
opened a channel with me yet wink wink
nudge nudge guy
uh but that means that with this
particular channel i'll be able to send
out
but not receive and we'll cover that
portion of it later
as we look at other channels so we will
continue to check on this
uh once it opens but in the meantime
let's look at how to open a channel in a
different way
so we're gonna go back to thunderhub
here
we'll just go back to home so we can
kind of recenter ourselves
and what we want to do is we're going to
be opening a channel
with another individual but we're going
to do
a push payment as we do it and so what
that means is i'm locking up bitcoin in
a lightning channel
and i'm simultaneously shifting some of
that bitcoin to the ownership of
somebody else
at the same time so the reason you might
do this is
one if you already owe somebody some
sats
and you want to open a lightning channel
with them you can pay them at the same
time
and you can designate that as we set it
up or
if you would like to set up a lightning
channel with somebody
mutually who you know and you agree that
okay we want the channel to be well
balanced so we
both can send back and forth right off
the hop
what you can do is you can push half of
it half of the liquidity
uh over to the other individual and then
they can send you a regular bitcoin
transaction
back so let's say you were opening a
channel for two million sats with
somebody
and you want them that you want a
well-balanced channel
as you open it you can push one million
of those sats half of it to the person
in the lightning channel and then
they'll send you a transaction to your
regular bitcoin wallet for 1 million
sets
so you both have the spending ability
and the receiving ability and you're all
squared off and even so nobody's losing
money in that transaction
so let's take a look at how to do that
again
we go down and i have an individual same
idea here
i want to open a channel with this
individual
i currently owe them some sats and so
this is their node
and this is the information that they
sent me in terms of
the connection info and again you don't
have to open up one ml if somebody sends
you the information but i just wanted to
represent it on the screen here
and just as before on our main home
screen we go to open
and manual will hit the open button
again
now is this a new peer yes it is
you paste in the information for the
node now what is the channel size going
to be i'm going to
do another 1 million sat channel
now this is the part where we use the
push tokens to partner
option so in this case it's a specific
number of sats that i'm pushing to this
person
um so i'm not going to do the half i'm
going to do
custom and 41
31 5. so 41 315 sets
is what is outstanding what i owe this
individual and that will get pushed to
them as i open this
and then what do we need for sats per
byte
again this one i'm not in as much of a
rush oh
there's i don't know if you heard the
little uh queue there but my transaction
was just confirmed from before
um i'm not in as much of a rush with
this channel so i'll set it a little bit
lower i'll probably do about
30 sats per byte should probably do me
maybe
yeah maybe 30 sets per byte okay so i'll
just put that information in
30. everything else looks good to me so
i'm going to go ahead and i'm gonna hit
open channel
just as before
okay channel is opened and so what i've
done
is i've opened a channel with this
individual let's go into our channels
over on the left hand side here and
go into pending just hit a quick
refresh there pending one more time
okay there is the new channel that i've
just opened up i can click on it
and again uh if i want i can
track that transaction by copying the
transaction id here
and heading over to
[Music]
mempool.space let's just have a
different window for it and i can just
track that by the way
the reason i'm opening a new window this
mempool.space is
linked to the umbral node so it's like a
private kind of set of data
rather than connecting to the internet
but if you just click
on the transaction id it will open up in
the regular website as well
okay um so anyways there's my
transaction
waiting to get through but effectively
what i've done is i've paid
this person as i open up the channel and
once that channel is open they will see
that they have
uh 41 000 sats on their side of it so i
have paid them at the same time
perfect so we basically have two
channels
now just waiting to be confirmed and uh
and and we're off to the races now there
is one other way
one other way to go ahead and open a
channel
and this is actually the first thing
i ever did when i started up this
lightning node
what i'm going to do here is i'm going
to open a channel with a
pretty big node that isn't necessarily a
merchant because
if i open with a merchant then and i
have a lot of other peers connected to
me
i may find that that channel drains
rather quickly
what i want is i want to open up a
channel with a large node
so one of the largest nodes that's easy
to uh
to find go to 1ml right here
is async okay and you see it right here
top channel count increase they're
always up top they're one of the biggest
nodes out there
async right there and
it's yeah it's the number one in terms
of channels so it's the largest
out there the most for capacity and so
the reason
i'm going to open a channel with these
individuals is i'm going to do something
called a loop
out and this is kind of like the push
that i just did
with the last opening channel um where
i'm going to create a channel
with a large amount of sats allocated to
it
but then i'm going to use a service
called lightning loop
to send bitcoin through that channel
to async and then route it to
lightning labs and lightning labs in
turn
will then send me a regular bitcoin
transaction
back now why might i do this same reason
as wanting a balanced channel before
this is so that i have a large amount of
inbound capacity so i can accept a lot
of
payments via lightning network in the
future
and so this is what i did actually we
can even go and look at my
my async channel from before
so we can see it is right here up top
so this was a 10 million satoshi channel
and i opened that initially and
uh then i looped out 8 million sats so i
still had some spending capacity
but you can see now the balance started
to shift
on my side there's 3.2 million and on
their side there's 6.8 million
so this means that i can accept 6.8
million
sats worth of payments through this
particular channel
so if this is seeming a little bit over
your head let's just go through the
steps and see what it looks like
so i've got the async node right here
this is the information i need to
connect to them
i'm going to copy that information
now i'm going to go over to thunderhub
i'm going to go channels
then i'm going to or sorry i'm going to
go home rather
and i'm going to go to the open
at this point we're going to
hit the manual open as well
now this is the interesting part if i
was opening up a channel with somebody
i'm already connected
to i would do the drop down and i can
see
async is in here right there
that's the same information as before
it's the same node everything
i could designate a certain number of
sats
1 million 10 million whatever it's going
to be
i'm not going to push because we're
doing a loop
if i push in this case i don't know
who's at async nobody knows that i'm
doing this they'll just have
extra money and they won't know why so
this is not what i'm trying to do
okay so i'm not pushing
and then you would set your sas per byte
and you would open a channel
let's just pretend i already went
through those steps and
we're going to refer back to my already
open channel with async
so let's just pretend that i had opened
a channel
and i already had
funds allocated to async here and
it was a 3.2 million satoshi channel
okay i want some of that back
so that i can open up other channels in
the future i just want the ability to
receive the funds through async because
they're really well connected
well what can we do we can use
something called and let me re-log into
my umbrella here
we can use something called lightning
loop or something through lightning labs
called loop
and so this is in the app store it is
lightning terminal that's the one that
you want you just download it i've
already downloaded it
i can click on it and log in by the way
the default password on
umbral unless you change it is money
printer go burr
okay and this is lightning terminal i'm
not going to get super deep into exactly
all that's here this will be a future
video as well
but may be useful for some of you
setting up your first channels
so let's assume that you created a large
channel with async
and all of the capacity is on your side
so you can spend out pretty easily but
you still can't receive payments
you can change that balance by
on the first tab here under lightning
terminal hitting the loop button
you're gonna find that channel that is
async
and then you're going to choose loop out
this is where you're taking money out of
lightning network
and back into your regular bitcoin
wallet now right here
you're going to choose the amount of
sats i'm just going to do 1 million sats
because i've got about 3 million in
capacity to send out i don't want to
pull too much out of that for right now
it is in your best interest to pull a
larger amount in that it cuts down on
the
fees that you're gonna pay here you've
got two fees to contend with
the the loop fee which is half a percent
and the on chain transaction fee okay
if you want under additional options
here
you can set a confirmation target so if
you're
not interested in waiting a super long
or if you don't mind waiting a super
long time and you want lower fees
sure you can put in a certain number of
blocks
or you can change the address that you
would like to receive to
the default is just the address of your
own
umbrella node which i'm going to leave
so i'm not going to change anything here
i'm going to hit next i can see
yes it is gonna be a bit of a steep fee
it's 1.67 percent of the total lot
and a good portion of that is just the
on-chain fee because
i'm not optimizing for what i'm doing
right now
again ideally i'd be doing a larger
chunk of
a larger channel but hey that's okay
this just for
educational purposes so anyways um i'm
gonna go ahead i
this is fine i'll eat the fee for right
now
and i'm going to hit confirm and so what
this does
is it's saying to lightning labs hey
this person
will send you 1 million sats via
lightning
plus a fee if you send them
one million sats to their own bitcoin
wallet and that's what's taking place
right now
okay so this does take a while to
execute um
sometimes it can be quite a while i i
think i've waited an hour for this
previously but that's because also
you're you're settling on chain
lightning labs has their own thing in
the background that does loop
so it's it's a useful tool if you're
trying to get
inbound capacity while setting up your
node and you maybe don't have peers yet
that want to
open up channels with you so use the
tools that you have
we will check back on this momentarily
once all of this gets sorted including
those earlier channels
all right when the loop is finished you
will see the loops complete
thing here that is all set um
i can head back to umbrol and if i go
to my home uh i should see
yep there is in my bitcoin wallet a
deposit
just shy of a million sats so they
actually take the fee
from the million that i looped out so
there's the deposit eight minutes ago
that came in uh so that is all set i can
also see that my older transaction
opening a channel with guy swann is
very well confirmed as well as the other
the other
transaction opening the channel with the
person that i pushed a payment to so
those are
both all set so let's take a look in
thunderhub and again
just to refresh you moving from our home
screen here you would just go to
channels on the left hand side and i can
see here
uh the async one remember it was two
point around two point three million
well or it was three point three million
sats was on my
side of the channel well now that has
shifted over
so i sent a million through that channel
to pay lightning labs
and that was paid back to me main chain
now i also i believe can scroll down i
just got to find them here
there's crypt economy there we go
there's that channel that i just opened
there and i can't remember the name
of the other channel that i had it
should be
somewhere around here there it is right
there 41.3 k
so there's that push payment so i opened
a channel and i paid the person at the
same time
so we basically have opened three
channels
uh in three different ways we have done
it with a regular open where all the
capacity stays on my side and i can
spend easily
we've done it with a push payment where
i paid somebody in the process
splitting up some of the capacity and
then we've done
a regular channel open with a loop out
which
got me bitcoin back on the main chain
while maintaining some liquidity in the
channel so i can receive lightning
payments
later fun okay
in the process we did get some inbound
liquidity but really quick let's review
how somebody might connect with you
in order to get capacity uh on
their side to be able to send out and
you'll notice
in my channels you'll notice some of
them where
all of the capacity is on the other side
and this is a channel where somebody has
opened
with me and all of the bitcoin is on
their side but if they
route a payment through my node we will
notice that shift over and start to
spill
into the my side of the channel you can
also
see let's see bitcoiner support open a
channel with me mr nice node myno btc
so there's a number of individuals that
have opened
channels with me where there hasn't been
a movement of funds as of yet
but there's a lot of different channels
anything in blue is on my side
meaning that i can spend anything in
green is on their side
meaning that i can receive or they can
all be used to route payments from
others that are just connected us to us
in some way
without costing me any money in fact you
actually can gain some fees
from doing that now again for somebody
to connect to you
all you need to do go to your home
screen you can copy your public key
and give them that or you can just hit
the copy onion button and that
copies the entire chain that they need
to connect directly to you
and that's pretty much it
now in terms of in inbound capacity you
can do
it other ways as well so if you can't
find somebody to connect to you
i highly recommend that you do try that
uh jump on bitcoin twitter start
tweeting out
uh tag a few people see who you can find
there are telegrams
groups for this type of stuff so be sure
to
to look around you'll definitely be able
to find some people
however you can also rent
inbound liquidity so if you're a
merchant and you know you're going to be
accepting a lot of different lightning
lightning payments but you don't have
inbound liquidity
liquidity you can actually rent that um
you can do it through
somebody like bit refill they do have
thor
channels and basically it's you paying
to have them lock up their bitcoin and
open a channel with you so that you can
receive
payments you don't have to do this but
if you're in a pinch might be an option
so you can see
about 11 or 12 bucks to get a 1 million
sat channel open to you
now this does have some limitations they
will keep it open for 30 days
if there is no movement on that channel
if there's no consistent movement of
funds
then they may close the channel on you
so just keep that in mind
um this isn't like the the best way to
do it
but it is definitely an option
alternatively
we were on uh we were on lightning
terminal and this will be a future video
but you can actually uh join a
marketplace
and pay individuals to lock up their
bitcoin
and open channels with you using
lightning pool
but that is for another day and i
digress so we're going to
uh finish up with the channel talk and
let's assume that it took you a little
while to kind of get things
under control and get some channels
going it may take you a while to get
yourself well set up
but once you start having some capacity
on both sides with some well connected
channels
then it's time to start doing
transactions and that's what we're going
to take a look at next
so to receive transactions directly to
your lightning node
really simple just from your home screen
under your accounts
and then the lightning account here
there is a receive button
and you're going to create a lightning
invoice for a certain number of sats
that you would like to receive
i'm just going to do a small one for
1000 satoshi's
you can enter a description if you like
or an expiry i'm not going to do either
of those things i'm just going to go
ahead and hit
create invoice now this gives me a
lightning invoice in
text which i could hit the copy button
and then i could paste that into a
message to somebody
or for a certain amount of time it
counts down
this qr code will be available as well
so just within
i'm using blue wallet right now just as
a proof of concept
i'm going to do a quick scan of that i
can see the invoice pops up on my wallet
and tells me it's a thousand sats
and i'm just gonna hit pay and that
should show up
in no time at all hopefully approved
via my node so there we go i can see it
says paid and it says the same
on my phone sorry for the reflection but
you get the point
so that's how you receive regularly via
an invoice and you can do that for any
amount that you like assuming that you
have the capacity
to receive that via one of your channels
now another way
and this is an interesting one that you
can do
is key send
now what is key send key send is
somebody sending directly to your node
so let me just get my information here
my node information
okay so i'm going to copy that i'm going
to
head right over to 1ml that website
we've been using
and there's my node okay and this is my
node information key send allows you to
send directly to an individual's node
without having to create invoices now
i'm going to be doing this
via breeze okay via breeze wallet
this is another lightning wall that i've
done tutorials on i've got about 10
000 sats sitting in it right now and i'm
gonna try
sending over just ten or not ten
thousand just a thousand sats
via key sent now not every lightning
wallet allows for this
there are certain reasons why there's no
payment trail when it comes to key sand
somebody could pretend that you didn't
pay them
so this is probably better used for like
tipping
all right so if you're going to give
somebody a tip then you can do a key
send
directly to their node all right and
if you want them to notice it you might
want to let them know that you did it
okay
but for this i can just hit the scan
button and i can simply
scan the node and then it prompts me
within breeze
how much do you want to send so i'm just
going to hit 1000
and i'm going to hit pay and it says are
you sure you want to send a thousand
sats to this node
and i confirm that and then it will
create
what's known as a key send transaction
direct to that node
there will be no notifications or
anything like that
but if i go back and i look in my
transactions
on my node uh then i will see it it does
say
payment was successfully sent so i can
head over
and i should be able to
uh just hit refresh here and see if i've
got an
incoming transaction
indeed okay so i can see there's a
thousand sats
uh coming in from 16 seconds ago
so all set um that has been received
and two different ways to receive via
lightning
now what about sending out that's what
we're going to do next
so let's practice spending or
sending out some lightning transactions
from our node now that we're all well
connected and we know we can receive
so um i have brought up something i just
want to buy
uh this is bitcoinshirt.com and they
have a red hoodie here
hashtag reckless with a lightning symbol
so
why not let's let's grab this so i've
already gone through
filled out my info and i have a btc pay
invoice here and any time that you're uh
spending bitcoin oftentimes with btc
pays over you can toggle between
bitcoin and lightning network so this is
a lightning network
invoice i can just hit copy here
and it is a bolt 11 invoice if i just
tap that it will copy all that
information
i can then head over to my thunderhub
and we're going to in your accounts
under lightning we're going to hit send
now if you want you can actually go down
and hit decode and paste in
your addre or your invoice here and
it'll tell you
what's going on what you're sending who
you're sending to
so on and so forth so here it says hey
it's going to be paid to bitcoin shirt
store um there it's a counting down
here's the amount um all of this stuff
it lets you know kind of
what's going what the hops are going to
be in between
what's likely to happen so and so forth
so we're going to just try this out this
looks all good to me
i'm going to paste in that invoice
now what is the max fee that you would
uh like to pay so again
with each hop there may be you may be
incurring
like a satoshi or two fee so i don't
mind
having a fee that is
you know a a few sats or whatever it may
be
so i'm gonna set my my fee to
uh a hundred sats it's not gonna be that
much
probably but it kind of gives me that
wiggle room max pass i usually just
leave this at one
and if you want to you can choose which
channel it goes out through
but just be aware if you choose one that
doesn't have the liquidity or the path
you may have a failed payment so let's
just try that out i'm going to go ahead
i'm going to hit
pay all right payment is sent
let's jump back over to that invoice
invoice has been paid
all good so we were able to successfully
send out i'll have myself a new hoodie
whenever that ships out
great that's fantastic i'm going to
close these
out so that is one way
to pay now i previously mentioned
receiving via key send now we're going
to actually
send a transaction via key send and
again this is better used i'd say for
tips more than anything
uh but i digress let's take a look here
so there is an awesome dude who spent
some time with me teaching me a lot of
this stuff
and i'm still very new to a lot of it
but he was uh
kind enough to sit down on a call with
me for like
oh well over an hour to uh explain a lot
about thunderhub and
and help me wrap my head around of it um
his name
is nate uh and on twitter at beef
or bacon one uh well worth a follow he
was also on bitcoin kindergarten podcast
you can find the episode on youtube and
any other podcast
where he explains a lot of what we're
going through today anyways i appreciate
him and his time
so let's do a key sent to his node which
i have pulled up here
and all we need is we just need the
public key of that node so i'm going to
copy that right now
we'll jump back to thunderhub and just
as before we go into
our main page your accounts under
lightning we're going to hit
send the first thing we're going to do
it says is this a key send we're going
to hit
yes this time and then we're going to
paste in
the public key we're going to hit decode
and at that point it says hey uh
how much do you want to send so um you
know
he was pretty awesome with me so i'm
gonna go ahead
i'm gonna send the dude 50 000 sats
all right so we'll shoot that off we'll
just hit send
payment sent so there you go 50k sass
dude thank you for your time
much appreciated uh and i highly
recommend everybody go
check it out um of course unless he
watches this he may not realize that has
happened
but uh either way i i hope he enjoys the
sets
so that is sending now i did want to
reiterate a couple other things about
sending so just taking a look at the
send screen when we hit send
i kind of glossed over the the max paths
thing
earlier what this does is if you try to
send a transaction through a single path
just going through one node to the next
node to the next node to the next node
you may run into bottlenecks and that
means you may run into instances
where there's not enough capacity to
just jump from node to node to send off
a transaction
if that fails you can bump up this
number
and what that means is maybe if you go
just two to two paths it means it splits
your payment
amongst different channels and can go
out and then coalesce
on that singular destination so you're
paying
through two different routes the reason
you may not do this initially
is because it can incur higher fees but
keep that in mind and you can tinker
with these numbers as you go to try and
get your payment to go through
successfully
if having a relatively low fee and a
single path
does not work for you i hope that makes
sense
so now that we've basically got a well
set up node we've got lots of channels
in and out
liquidity on both sides of those we've
practiced sending and receiving
transactions
let's dig a little bit deeper into
what's in front of us and what
information and settings we can tinker
with
within our node okay so what i want to
look at right now is our list of
channels so over on the left hand side
we click on channels
and as i'm sure you figured out this is
a list of every channel that we have
open either to us or that we have opened
with somebody else
and when you hover over this you can see
the local and remote balance anything
blue again is what i can spend that is
local anything green is what i can
receive and that is remote
okay so you can see for instance this
channel up top somebody opened with me
sat base.org apparently 10 million sats
so i mean looks like they'd like to
route a lot of payments through me
great wonderful but i can know i cannot
spend out through them until some
comes in towards me and i gain some
liquidity there but either way
great um you can see as we go down async
i do have
a little bit more of a balance i can
send out
around 2 million sats and inbound
getting close to around 8 million sats i
can receive
this one in the middle wallet of satoshi
requarts
pear tree they're all pretty balanced
sending and receiving
on both ends now you may notice
some of your channels may show up as red
that means for the time being
the peer is currently offline and you're
not going to be able to utilize that
channel to
do payments now if i click on any
particular node and we'll just use the
red one
as an example it shows all kinds of
different information here
the local balance and remote balance it
also shows you
how much you've received through this
channel and how much you've sent through
the channel
and any reserves that have been put off
to the side you can see the
nodes public key which you can click on
and see all their other channels
the transaction id that was used to open
the channel
you can also and this is relevant for
this offline peer you can see the age of
the channel
and the time offline versus the time
online now this guy's only been offline
for about an hour and a half
over the past two and a half days
i'm not super worried about that he may
just have had uh internet outage or
something like that right
now that he's trying to figure out maybe
he's not home to reboot his router
again not worried but if you see
somebody that's been offline for a vast
majority
maybe it's time to think about closing
that channel out because the pier is
relatively unresponsive now in order to
actually close a channel
you can hit the close channel button
down below i'm not going to be doing
this but
if they are responsive you it says do
you want to force close the channel you
can just keep that on no
and then you just hit a a fee an
on-chain fee
that you're willing to pay to close out
the channel and then you just hit
close here so i could hit 10 sets per
byte if i'm not in
a rush or whatever and hit close channel
now if the person is
unresponsive that's when you would hit
yes to force closed channel
and it will just use the some of the
reserves in order
to close out that channel either way i'm
gonna leave this one running i am happy
with it
and uh that's pretty much that there's
one other thing that you can do
and i want to show you this um in
comparison
okay so let's go to hmm
let's go to my bit refill channel
okay so you can actually hit update
details
and this is where you can set your fees
now the fees here there's a base fee
which means if
any if any transaction is routed
through this channel of yours there will
be a minimum charge of one sat
that's basically as low as you can go
great wonderful um
now you also set a fee rate when you
initially start off this will be set to
one
effectively zero percent um however
if you notice that certain channels
drain quicker
that a lot of people are trying to route
through you you can
easily bump up the fees on those
channels
you may not want to do that right off
the bat as you're establishing yourself
but as you find
more transactions are being routed
through you can bump this up
a good starting place might be 250 which
is
0.025 percent
so still very very low some people have
it up around 300
for this one because i know it is a
merchant and
more people wrote transactions through
them i'm okay with 500
so it's kind of up to you if you start
setting it too high and you notice
transactions are no longer going through
it you can lower but this can constantly
be changed
whenever you like okay um
one that i've noticed that i've routed
quite a few through
is wallet of satoshi um i have that one
up quite high
i put it at a thousand i don't know that
any have been routed through there but
i'm just kind of testing the waters and
this
is this is kind of what you can do with
lightning you can tinker and see what
works and what doesn't it was previously
at 500 there was still a lot of
transactions going through but hey uh
feel free to play around with this
don't worry too much about your fees you
can
tinker and see what works for you
now you may find that certain channels
always tend to drain in a certain
direction
either remote or a local where you can
send a lot out
but you can't receive a lot constantly
or where you can receive a lot but you
can't send a lot
just based on the direction of
transactions that you are routing what
you can do
if you find this happens a lot espec
especially with particular channels is
you can use the
rebalance function here in thunderhub so
just along the side
there's a rebalance tab that you can
click on and here
you're brought to a screen where you
select the outgoing channel and the
incoming channel and effectively you're
bumping some sats from one channel over
to the next
to make things balance out a little bit
so on the outgoing side
i know that i've got a channel with bit
refill which is
relatively well connected that is
entirely local
okay so i can send but i basically can't
receive much of anything through there
now on the incoming side
there are a number of different nodes
that i have uh
you know mostly incoming and no outgoing
okay so here's one where
uh i've got only 10 of capacity is on my
side
and the rest is on the other side so
maybe i would like to route
some sats through bit refill and have it
come out on the other side of this
channel so that things are a bit more
balanced
so i've chosen my two routes that i'd
like to go through
and at this point we need to set the
fees that we would be okay with
paying in the process of rebalancing
these channels
and these are kind of like a maximum
that you're willing to pay now for this
i don't mind paying i don't know
let's say let's call it 2000 sats and
it's not gonna get up that
i'm i'm setting it that high so it's
more likely that it'll work for this
tutorial but you can keep it quite low
and then just poke and prod and see what
turns out for you
um they started at at 10 sats just to
to give you an idea but i'm just hedging
my bets and then at max
fee rate the highest i had set on any of
my channels was a thousand i don't even
know if anything's going through them so
i'll just set that as my my lower end a
lot of people are going to look at that
and say that's crazy that's way too high
again just i'm just hedging my bets
because i don't want to tinker too much
while i'm doing this
next you're going to choose the amount
that you would like to route through
to to bump um between the channels
you can do a fixed amount where you're
like i need this amount to go through or
you can do a target amount where you're
like
if it comes up a little bit short no big
deal i'm going to do target
and i'm going to do 600 000 sats just to
kind of see how that goes
if you want you can avoid certain nodes
if you know there's ones that have
stupidly high fees you can put that in
there
everything looks good to me so i'm going
to hit the rebalance button see how it
pans out
now of course this is dependent on it
finding a route between these two
channels
who knows if that will happen and it has
to be within the confines
of the fees that i set we shall see
a few moments later
so it didn't go through not a big deal
again i
just wanted to show you the example it
could have been that there were
uh there wasn't the liquidity in some of
the channels along the way that it found
not a big deal this is just something
that you can tinker with if you choose
to i have successfully rebalanced
in the past so just know that that's not
necessarily representative of it
but um as i suspect
with a lot of lightning stuff it will
continue to become
easier and easier to do this into the
future but at least you know the basics
now
we can dig into some of the data that we
do get through our node here there's a
few things that i found interesting
one of them is if you go to the forwards
tab and click
you can see the channels that are most
frequently
used in routing payments i can see that
going in through the stacking stats
through the tftc node
and out through wallet of satoshi it's
routed eight payments that way
in fact routing channels or routing
payments out through the wallet of
satoshi one
have been quite frequent and stacking
sats seems to
have a lot of ones coming in through it
at least 12 of them that i can see here
you can see a count along the side
um now you can also see up here you can
see a count based on
uh whatever time frame you're looking at
so this is kind of zoomed in but
based on the week how many payments you
wrote it i did 34 on
one day there five ten seven so it
depends how well connected you are
you can see how many sats were sent
total on a particular day
and then you can also click on fees and
see the fees in total
that you have collected and how much
i've gone through on certain days so
460 that day one day it was 2 000 sats
that came through
it just really depends on what your fees
are set but
interesting to look at nonetheless you
can also see
grouped by channel incoming and outgoing
you can see which ones are heavy on one
side or the other
and which ones are a little bit more
balanced or probably the smaller ones
but yeah a lot of good stuff to look at
through there now
another interesting thing that i found
here is under
stats on the left hand side and here you
can see info about your note i'll just
give it a quick little refresh to make
sure it's up to date
so it gives you kind of a score on your
node statistics
flow means how many channels are
actually having activity through them
you can scroll through and see how
they rank of course a lot of people have
opened
channels with me that maybe haven't done
any volume yet it's a relatively new
node so
maybe this will improve over time
you can also see uh uptime stats of
various nodes that are connected to you
most of mine are pretty good
but you know if i'm looking at some and
they look a little suspect
and they're getting down low maybe it's
time to think about closing out channels
but
again the note is too new to to really
worry about that too much
you can see fee stats from other
individuals what their
nodes are set to and then you can also
see your own fee stats
as to what it ranks as a pretty good fee
so even the ones that i have a little
bit higher like that are set at around
it says very good base fees and parts
per million fees or the the 250.
when you start getting above 250 i can
see like async it it gives it a little
less of a good rating
but i still have uh transactions being
routed through there so i'm not worried
about that but
um some interesting info that you can
glean from that
and very very useful and the last thing
i
really want to touch on here is i really
want to touch on
backing up your channel states
okay so yes when you set up your umbral
node you have
a uh you you do have a seed phrase
that you back up and you store safely
and that
does pertain to all of your bitcoin on
that node
however you'd also want to back up your
channel states for your lightning node
and the way you do that
is in the tools tab you hit on tools
and then you can see an option that says
backup
all channels and you just hit download
and you want to do this
basically relatively frequently honestly
when i'm on my note every time i'm on
here
um once a day once every couple of days
at the very least i would say once a
week
give this a download and just have it as
a file
where you can readily use it and even
back it up
elsewhere you know pull it on to an sd
or even
encrypted cloud storage whatever you
want but just have a copy of that
in case something happens to your node
you will be able to re-access all of
these channels and nobody can kind of
run away with money
or say that they hadn't paid you
and try to close the channel so and so
forth people can kind of mess around
with that
if you don't have the channel states um
and then finally if you do want to
recover this is where you would do it
you'd come back here
and you'd hit the recover button and use
that same file that you just downloaded
and you will recover all of your channel
states that
is pretty much that
this is so much you guys i apologize
this was a lengthy one
uh but hopefully you find this useful
obviously i'm gonna miss things i may
misspeak
this is also new to me don't take me as
like the gospel of lightning and
thunderhub
i'm doing my best here i hope
that this at least gets you guys to
start dabbling
and playing around and hopefully we'll
see
a ton more channels a ton more people
diving
into lightning network um and starting
to run their own nodes
and and tinker with channel management
thank you guys so much for watching
this one was an absolute doozy and there
were a lot of people
asking for this and i apologize that it
took me so long to get to it
but uh yeah it was quite the undertaking
anyways guys
um as always please do hit like
subscribe and share all of those things
help
so so much and uh get this out there to
whoever you think may find it useful
if you want to help us the show in
another way there's a few things you
could do you could hit up the sponsors
that i mentioned
down below that was leaden bit refill
and privacy pros dot io for the bill
funnel
or you could in uh in light of this
tutorial you could always drop me
a tip via key send directly
to my node i will link that in the show
notes so if you want to test that out
feel free to do so but uh maybe tweet at
me and let me know that you've done it
because otherwise i won't
really see it or know who did it again
with key send you don't get that
information
so feel free to do that and if you're
still
a little timid on the whole lightning
node thing and it's not quite set up yet
and you feel like dropping a tip you can
still tip via lightning
at my tip and dot me page using
something like breeze wallet or blue
wallet or something
that is just kind of a a download and go
lightning wallet for your phone
you can do that at tippin dot me slash
at btc
sessions that is p p i n dot me
slash at btc sessions
with that i am out have yourselves a
wonderful day or evening wherever you
may be
and i will see you guys next time for
your
daily session
you